Guide to the Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection 2010.020
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Green, Pamela, 2010 May 26; 2010.020.019
  Pamela Green was born in Gulfport, Mississippi in 1948. Green has a bachelor's degree in mathematics and began her career in 1968. She has worked for International Business Machines (IBM) and First National Bank of Chicago. She was a commissioner with city government in New York until becoming an executive with the Children's Television Workshop, the production company of Sesame Street. After being laid off in 2001, she became Executive Director of what was then the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Green oversaw the restoration of historic homes on the site and a name change to the Weeksville Heritage Center in 2005. Three years later, plans for a new Education and Cultural Arts Building were implemented and building began. She retired from the center in summer of 2013. Green was a resident of Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn for decades, and also has a master's degree in finance from the University of Chicago.
  Pamela Green is interviewed in her professional role as Executive Director of the Weeksville Heritage Center in Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood. Green covers the history of the site as well as the institution, describes the historic houses, the educational mission, the programs and events, the planned expansion, funding, other goals, and the approach to exhibitions. She discusses the beginning of her involvement and her contributions as executive. Green returns to the topic of Weeksville's founding and addresses the boundaries of the site in reference to the neighborhoods of Crown Heights and Bedford-Stuyvesant. She closes with advice on education for young people. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Civil rights |z New York (State) |z New York; African Americans |x Colonization; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historical museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Race relations |z United States; Slavery |z United States |x History; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Green, Pamela; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
- Green, Richard, 2010 June 17; 2010.020.020
  Richard Green was born in Tela, Honduras in 1948 and grew up in various locations in Brooklyn. He graduated from Erasmus Hall High School, served in the Marines, achieved an undergraduate degree at Marist College and attended a graduate program at the State University at New Paltz. Beginning in 1969, he was a permanent fixture of the Crown Heights neighborhood and raised his children there. In 1977, Green founded the Crown Heights Youth Collective and he still served as the Chief Executive Officer in 2016. He also co-founded the Street Outreach Program, has worked with five New York mayors as of 2016, and assisted with Project Cure, a community healing organization formed in the wake of the Crown Heights riot. Since 1993, he has taught as an adjunct professor at Medgar Evers College. He has served on boards, as a trustee or a member, of several high-profile government and public services departments for New York City. Green has been heard on radio as a commentator and producer. He is a husband, father and grandfather.
  Richard Green speaks briefly about his upbringing in Brooklyn. He speaks at length about the informal beginnings of the Crown Heights Youth Collective and in general about the meaning of youth centers to a community. Park gatherings were an early form of the collective. Green reflects on when he met Cecil Simon, the co-interviewer as well as a narrator of another oral history in this collection. Simon asks for Green's observations on changes in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Green traces the recent history of the area, including the relationship between the Black and Hasidic communities, the riot in 1991, and the two decades that followed. Simon discusses his high school experience, the importance of literacy and kindness in street culture, and his incarceration. Richard Green speaks about the teens with whom he works, their assumptions and the collective's workspace. He relays the historical benchmarks of many areas in Brooklyn. Green opines on redevelopment and the fallout in communities. He comes back to the Crown Heights Youth Collective, where he instills values and goals in the members. Interview conducted by Cecil Simon and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Barclays Center (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race identity; Race relations |z United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights Youth Collective (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Richard; Robinson, Jackie; Simon, Cecil
- Gruber, Edward, 2010 March 25; 2010.020.021
  Edward Gruber was born at Brooklyn Jewish Hospital in 1937 and raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood until he was eighteen. He attended P.S. 241, near Ebbets Field, which afforded him frequent stops to Dodgers games on his way home. His family's home was a brownstone on the north side of Eastern Parkway. He attended Erasmus Hall High School, graduated in 1955, and went on to Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, New York. Gruber had a career as a telecommunications engineer and manager for International Telephone & Telegraph Corporation (ITT). When he first married, he lived on Long Island. At the time of the interview in 2010, he lived with his wife in Northern New Jersey and their daughter and grandson were new residents in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood.
  Ed Gruber begins the interview by noting that he was born in the neighborhood's Brooklyn Jewish Hospital, lived on Eastern Parkway, and that he has been a repeat visitor to Brooklyn's Crown Heights since leaving for college in 1955. He observes the renewal on this 2010 visit, including new stores on Franklin Avenue, coffee shops, and a construction site. He reflects on a visit to a butcher shop in his youth and his father's reporting to air raid headquarters on Franklin Avenue for duty as a warden in 1940s wartime. He tells of his grandfather's time as a restaurateur and a bartender. Gruber would walk his dog past the Town Hill nightclub to see who was singing there. He recalls the trolley on Eastern Parkway, attending P.S. 241 and seeing Dodgers games, Franklin D. Roosevelt's motorcade and, from his stoop, the Memorial Day parade. Gruber talks about childhood games he played, going to Erasmus Hall High School and getting a driver's license. He remembers seeing stores that were looted or closing down in the early 1960s and he shares some of his grandmother's recollection of the neighborhood in the early 1900s. Gruber mentions he has come back for school reunions, and even got involved with a reunion committee for P.S. 241. He closes with some praise for Brooklyn and words of wisdom for schoolchildren of this era. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York; Restaurateurs |z New York (State) |z New York; Transportation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Erasmus Hall High School; Gruber, Edward; Jewish Hospital of Brooklyn
- Guthrie, Douglas, 2010 May 3; 2010.020.022
  Douglas Guthrie was born in 1950 in Jamaica and, along with a brother and sister, was raised there by his parents. In the early 1960s his mother immigrated to England and because of that split between his parents, Guthrie was shipped to a boarding school. One of a few musicians in the family, he studied music on a scholarship and co-founded the reggae group Inner Circle. He was on tour as an alto saxophone player with that band in the early 1970s when he first saw America. He joined the punk band The Nails in 1972. He moved to Crown Heights in 1975, sharing a home with his first wife, his mother-in-law and a brother. After twelve years, when the couple had their first child, they moved to Flatbush and later, Canarsie, to make more room at home. Divorced, Guthrie returned to Crown Heights in 1998. By this time he had moved on to composing and performing with reggae, ska and dub band the Motives, and continued with them until 2000. In 2010, Guthrie had adult children, a fiancé and a little girl. In 2011, he released a solo album, "Dougie Guthrie: Melody Maker."
  Douglas Guthrie begins the interview by explaining the moves he's made while living in Brooklyn. He recalls his arrival from Jamaica as a touring musician and his first impressions of Brooklyn's diverse Crown Heights neighborhood. Guthrie notes that Eastern Parkway splits the community geographically, but culturally as well. He describes his somewhat tumultuous childhood, focusing on music, and life as a musician in Crown Heights. Guthrie feels a need to work through the tension that remained in the community after the uprising in 1991 and discusses community involvement and acting as a peacemaker in social conflicts. He reminisces about his breakthrough in the music business by showing off his album covers and about being a working musician in Crown Heights. Guthrie talks about the West Indian Carnival; first in relation to his daughter's participation, and then by examining the problems and potential improvements that could be applied. He closes by advising young people to establish foundations and structure to excel at life. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte, Quanaisha Phillips and Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Jamaican Americans; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Music education; Musicians |z New York (State) |z New York; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z New York; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Guthrie, Douglas; Inner Circle (Musical group); Nails (Musical group); West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Kelly, Wilhelmena, 2010 April 12; 2010.020.023
  Wilhelmena Rhodes Kelly was born in 1948 and raised in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant until age thirteen. She and her sister, Linda Rhodes Jones, represent the third generation of the family to have lived in Brooklyn (Her grandparents bought a Bed-Stuy home in 1932). The family moved to Union Street in Crown Heights and Kelly attended that Brooklyn neighborhood's schools; Lefferts Junior High School, Erasmus Hall High School and Brooklyn College (class of 1970). Seeing a decline in services for the community in the early 1980s, Kelly relocated to Queens. Since 2004, Kelly has written or co-written two books of genealogical studies and two books of archival photos of Brooklyn neighborhoods. Now living in Rosedale, Queens, she began a chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution (the first woman of color to do so) in 2012 and served as regent. Kelly has promoted genealogy in workshops and online.
  Wilhelmena Rhodes Kelly opens the interview by speaking about her family's transition from the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood to the Crown Heights neighborhood in Brooklyn. She recalls the schools of the neighborhood in a time of new buildings to support the baby boom generation. Kelly discusses what inspired her to write. She chronicles her progress through school as well as the history of some place names and those who settled the area. Kelly compares Brooklyn of 2010 with her experience in Queens since the 1980s. She describes the history of her family in Crown Heights, referencing homes of her parents and grandparents. Kelly talks about her process of researching and writing a book on Crown Heights and shares some of the discoveries of her research. She reminisces about the fun she had as a Brooklyn youth, including riding horses and visiting Coney Island. Kelly closes with some advice for the Brooklyn youth of this era. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte, Quanaisha Phillips, and Alex Kelly.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Genealogy -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Local history; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn College; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Erasmus Hall High School; Kelly, Wilhelmina
- La Fontaine, Rosella Johnson, 2010 April 19; 2010.020.024
  Rosella Johnson La Fontaine was born in Brooklyn in 1934 and raised in homes on Adelphi Street and on Grand Avenue in the Clinton Hill neighborhood. Her mother was a Virgin Islands national and her father came from Nice, France. In the early 1950s, her family settled in a large house on Park Place at New York Avenue in the Crown Heights neighborhood. La Fontaine campaigned to save the nearby Brooklyn Children's Museum in the late 1960s and '70s and has been a community activist and a champion of community activism. Her home was given landmark status in 2011. La Fontaine died in 2015.
  In the interview, La Fontaine gives some brief background on her family's residences in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Clinton Hill. She shares her in-depth knowledge of the surrounding buildings and her own home. La Fontaine reflects on the efforts to save the Brooklyn Children's Museum from leaving or closing after challenges from fire and city government intervention. She discusses the area churches and important community leaders such as Reverend Clarence Norman, Sr., Dr. Adrian Edwards, former Assemblyman Karim Camara, Dianne Davis of Garden of Learning Day Care, Ora Abdur-Razzaq, founder and principal of the Cush Campus Schools, and an unheralded citizen, Annie Mae Hearston. La Fontaine returns to describing the architecture of her home and recalls her parents' search for the home. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Ansie Montilus and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Children's Museum; Camara, Karim; Dinkins, David N.; Girls' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Greene Avenue Baptist Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); La Fontaine, Rosella Johnson
- Lesold, Constance, 2010 April 7; 2010.020.025
  Constance "Connie" Lesold was born in North Carolina in 1938. She first visited the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1966 and had an apartment with her husband, Helmuth Lesold, by 1967. The couple had one son, Benjamin, who was born in 1970. She is a social worker, who was president of the Parkway Independent Democrats and an official of Community Board Eight. Along with her husband, several Brooklyn community boards, the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, and a public coalition, she opposed the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's move to end service on the Franklin Avenue Shuttle in the mid-1990s. A widow since 1994, she volunteered with the Brooklyn Mental Hygiene Court Monitors Project and became a member of Disabled in Action. In 2004, she joined a group occupying a firehouse that shut down service in Williamsburg. Lesold joined lawmakers and citizens at the Capitol in Albany to protest rent control regulations in 2015 and she remains an active participant in MTA Board hearings.
  Constance Lesold begins the interview by talking about her first memories of the Crown Heights neighborhood in 1966. She talks about her late husband, Helmuth Lesold, and the early years of their marriage in an apartment building on Eastern Parkway. Along with other residents, they petitioned their landlord to integrate their building. She remembers the dramatic change in the fall of 1967, when Whites became the minority in the diversifying community. Lesold refers to the multicultural school her son attended. She focuses on the battle to save the Franklin Avenue Shuttle from permanent closure and names the pivotal activists involved: her husband, Sybil Holmes, Community Boards Three, Eight and Nine, Borough Presidents Howard Golden and Marty Markowitz, Councilwoman Mary Pinkett, the Brooklyn Museum and the Brooklyn Botanic Garden. Lesold makes the point that there is still work to do in subway accessibility, and discusses the garden above the Franklin Avenue Shuttle that was vandalized by Transit Police. The Atlantic Yards Project, the Daily News' departure, and past efforts to get federal funding for neighborhoods are the other concerns for Lesold. She concludes with advice for young activists. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Environmentalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ocean Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subway stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subways |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban beautification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Botanic Garden; Brooklyn Museum; Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway Coalition; Golden, Howard; Lesold, Constance; Lesold, Helmuth; New York Daily News; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority
- Lipkind, Arna, 2010 May 17; 2010.020.026
  Arna Lipkind was born circa 1958 and raised in a suburb of Detroit, Michigan. She graduated from Seaholm High School and received a bachelor's degree in Special Education from Michigan State University. Lipkind moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn to teach, and also to attend a continuing education program provided by the Lubavitcher Rebbe that focused on religion. In 1990, she began volunteering for New York State Senator Marty Markowitz and supported him through his Borough Presidency until 2004. She was the Community Liaison for New York State Assemblymember Karim Camara from 2006 to 2009, Community Liaison for the New York City Council from 2009 to 2014 and District Manager of the same council from 2009 onward. She's an honoree of the Crown Heights Community Leadership Council, a wife to community activist Rabbi Reuven Lipkind and a mother of six.
  In the interview, Arna Lipkind describes the moment she heard the car crash that partly instigated the 1991 riot in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. She discusses her involvement in positive community dialogue as well as misperceptions between African American, Caribbean and Jewish communities, and Marty Markowitz's group forum "Can We Talk." Lipkind speaks about her lifestyle as a Hasidic Jewish woman in Crown Heights. She speaks at length on the differences in the Jewish sects of New York City. Lipkind emphasizes what her mentors have given her. Finally, she advises that learning happens every day and that is important to learn from people of "different backgrounds." Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait, Treverlyn Dehaarte, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z New York; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Michigan; Multiculturalism; Race relations |z United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women and religion |z New York (State) |z New York; Cato, Gavin; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Lipkind, Arna; Markowitz, Marty; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
- Louis, Marie, 2010 April 28; 2010.020.027
  The daughter to Haitian immigrants, Marie Louis was born at Kings County Hospital in 1972 and was raised on Carroll Street in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Louis attended P.S. 241 and Holy Spirit Catholic School, then known as St. Theresa's. She entered a medical professions program in high school and graduated from A. Philip Randolph High in Harlem. Louis was an event organizer and president of the Black Students Organization during her time at Columbia University. She grew up attending church at St. Ignatius Roman Catholic Church and then, as an adult, St. Gregory's. In 1995, she worked for the Youth Development Institute, and in 1998, the Community Counseling & Mediation program. She served on the board that attained a Community Benefits Agreement in relation to the Atlantic Yards Project and then joined Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (BUILD). Later, she became Chief Operating Officer of the organization. She married in 2007. After a six-month battle with cancer, she died in December, 2011. Among her survivors are her husband, five siblings and a son and daughter.